well first thanks a lot for having me
it's really exciting for me to be here
in front of like so many people that all
want to build cool things I was I was
getting ready for the talk last night
and I was going back through old emails
because times are memories little bit
hazy and I found an email from March
2010 which was roughly like three and a
half four months after we launched
Pinterest and it's an email to our
advisors and our investors at the time
and I thought I would read it to you
because I was kind of like a cool blast
from the past for me he mo says hey
everyone I wanted to provide a quick
update from cold brew labs which was our
company name just to review we launched
a website called Pinterest it's a tool
for people to share and discover the
things they love people join Pinterest
to create these collections or pin
boards in to follow collections created
by their friends we're happy to say that
we're making good progress today we have
almost 3,000 registered users and our
daily pin count is steadily increasing
I'm also happy to say that we've made
big operational improvements we're
relocating our offices to a new building
just a few blocks away the price will
decrease as we're sharing it with
another Y Combinator startup er do and
we've also gotten some free Amazon
hosting credits
so
a couple funny things about the email in
general the first is that the new
location in question is a dilapidated
two-bedroom apartment on California
Avenue and in fact when I told Jessica
Livingston that we were moving there she
said oh my god I thought that place was
a brothel and the second is the exact
setup of the place so we add two
bedrooms one of which my co-founder Paul
lived in in one of which Dave the
co-founder of giardia lived in this is a
picture of Dave and we worked out of the
living room these two companies all
together pretty much all day and Dave
was a late night guy who's hackers
hacker always up till 4:00 a.m. and so
when we were having meetings with
investors or with users every once in a
while Dave what kind of saunter out in
his towel because that was how you had
to get to the shower and just sort of
wave it everyone and it was really
awkward and so a little bit later when
we all got to go watch the social
network we made a pact that if anyone
ever made a movie about our company they
would get to be played by Ryan Gosling
because Ryan Gosling has awesome ABS so
the other thing though that's like a
little bit more serious if you think
about it for months in 3000 accounts for
consumer start up is really not very
good and I think the thing that
surprised me the most in starting a
company after reading about you know
Facebook hits Harvard 95% penetration in
two weeks like Instagram shoots to a
million people is that it can take a
really really long time to build things
that are worthwhile so March 2010 we
launched Pinterest where 3,000 accounts
and that wouldn't be so bad if we hadn't
started building Pinterest actually in
November 2009 and that alone wouldn't
have been so bad if I hadn't left my job
to start a company in May 2008
a lot of people say things like running
a startup is like running a marathon and
I think that the part of the analogy
that's right is that it's long but it's
actually really different I mean I think
when I think about my experience it's
more like going on a road trip like in a
car that doesn't have good headlights
and you don't have very much gas and you
think you're going to Toledo but you
find out you're supposed to be in Miami
and if you really run out of gas you
might have to buy gas for someone that
might just kick you out of your own
drivers seat and that uncertainty the
fact that every single day you're
dealing with a lot of choices you don't
have a lot of perfect information is for
me that's lesson that was hardest to
learn and continues to be real challenge
in doing it startup today so I'm going
to talk a little bit about kind of our
journey through this kind of weird
process and a few of the things that we
learned along the way number one lesson
making things can take a long time so
2008 I was working at Google and I was
in Adsense not as an engineer but
working basically doing customer support
taking feedback from users and feeding
it back into the advertising products
the reason I was there was because I'd
come from Washington DC where I was
working as a consultant and growing up
even though I always looked up to
anybody that made things whether it was
an architect or an engineer or an artist
I'd always kind of thought that I was
going to be a doctor and so I pursued
that path which is the same path my
parents pursued the same path that both
my sisters pursued so when I graduated
from college and decided I didn't want
to be a doctor I was a little bit lost
but even then like even at the time that
I thought I was going to be a doctor I
had this real interest in technology I
thought it was really cool so when I was
an undergrad I made a program with some
friends and let you try on glasses
online and it was appropriate because
both my parents were ophthalmologists
when I was at my consulting job in DC a
good friend of mine named alt I had me
help him out with his wife see startup
what he was trying to help market bands
he was a musician in a band and even
when I moved out to California I was at
Google I was working on another website
which was a quiz website to let anybody
play quiz questions about anything they
wanted and the common theme through all
these things was that for some reason I
kept going back to the idea of building
a product I thought that was a really
exciting thing to do but it always
stalled and I always had an excuse for
why it stalled it wasn't the right mark
I need to learn more by working at
Google it wasn't the right timing but
actually the dependent variable was just
me
all right the dependent variable was
that I never actually committed and put
myself in a situation where I had to
make it work and so I think for me I
paid too much attention to talks where
people basically build something huge on
the side and they were pulled out of
their job and everything was working for
me at least the act of committing to
going out and doing doing it turned out
to be a really important thing and so I
don't know if this applies to everyone
I've heard of a lot of people that have
successfully built things on the side
and then gently transition it into a
full-time gig but at least in my
situation for a person that really like
puts his heart into whatever job is at
hand it was a really important step I
actually remember the night that I made
the call
I was sitting at dinner with my
girlfriend then now my wife and I was
talking about some cool idea that I
think would be great how we could build
it how we could market it and she looked
at me and said you know you should
either do it or just just stop talking
about it
and it was a little bit harsh but
honestly it was the best thing someone
could have told me because she was
absolutely right and I feel genuinely
thankful that someone was honest enough
in my life to just call me out and say
make it happen or don't make it happen
but just make your call and be happy
with that call and so I'm always really
thankful for her getting me that advice
so I left in 2008 and I hooked up with
one of my friends named Paul he was a
great friend from college
super driven guy and we decided the
thing we were really interested in was
mobile so the iPhone had come out
recently in the platform had come out
and so people were really excited about
it
and the product that we wanted to build
was called tote it was a shopping
catalogue on the phone and the reason I
thought this would be so cool was that I
got all these catalogs in the mail
dumped on my doorstep and I had this
brand-new like really cool phone and I
just wanted to see something running on
this phone and so we got to work and we
started prototyping it we did it out of
savings but there were some problems the
first was that it took a really long
time to get things built and approved by
Apple like a really long time back then
you had no idea when I was going to get
approved you had no idea what's gonna
happen and second there were a lot of
unsolved problems back then we had sort
of these grand ideas of doing all sorts
of offline caching being able to use
this thing in the subway being able to
eventually process payments we put all
those ideas into this prototype and it
made it really hard to ship and not
surprisingly sooner or later we were in
a situation where we really needed to
raise some money and it was 2008 and you
had two non technical co-founders and it
was a really bleak time there are lots
of ways for investors to say no to you
and I'm pretty sure that I've heard all
of them like I've heard every single one
like these are the top three like number
one is call me back in a few months this
is kind of the most painful it's just
like you ask someone out on a date and
they're like not right now but maybe
maybe in November right that one that
one is like really really hard to hear
because you're gonna have even less
money and you can even have less
leverage in a negotiation the second is
who else is in alright this is one that
you hear all the time it's like it's not
good enough for me
by myself but if there are other people
to come money I'd be willing to consider
it and then there were the occasional
people that were really blunt they were
just like there's no way this is going
to happen this is
this is insane it's totally crazy I
remember really vividly I went to a
session where I was pitching actually a
whole group of investors up on Silicon
Valley and it's really intimidating
right you're looking and these people
that build great companies and I'm about
five minutes into explaining what we're
doing everyone starts just like heading
for the door and I was like man like
what what am I doing wrong
and I found out they had brought a tray
of free cookies and what I was saying
was interesting enough to keep them in
their seats as long as they were like no
cookies in the background you know we've
done fundraising a few times and
sometimes it's been easier and sometimes
it's been really really hard we've done
it where we've flown all the coasts
we've tracked down sort of everyone in
our alumni directory whether they were
tech investors are not investors we've
done it a bunch and I think I've learned
like three important lessons that I
think any entrepreneur should should
know if they're starting the kind of
company they think will need funding the
first is that my even rich people are
subject to free cookies right like even
even though you're really rich you're
probably still the kind of person that
is influenced by free and and in that
lesson is actually something really
important it's that investors are just
people - right
investors are just regular people that
happen to other people's money or their
own money that are willing to put
forward and even though they have a
really good opinion on things they might
be wrong and that was something that was
really hard for me to swallow because I
really looked up to all these people
you know the second lesson is that if
you really need money and they have
money and they know they're the only
person that can give you the money you
don't really have any leverage
whatsoever are you have zero leverage
and that puts you in a really tough spot
right you can't really negotiate it's
2008 they know it's 2008 they see your
app it's kind of crappy nobody really
uses it there's nothing you can do
unless you hack that system right unless
you somehow turn the tables and give
them a reason that you should have the
leverage and those reasons generally are
fear of losing the deal right or the
belief that this thing is just going to
be so big that whether you give the
money or not like you're just going to
be wildly successful
number two was a hard case for us to
sell so we solve for number one and that
was a really important thing and the
very last thing I learned and this was
something that was especially true when
you're kind of driving up Sand Hill Road
which I don't know if you guys have been
to I sort of thought I would look like
the Emerald City but it kind of looks
like a ski lodge with no mountain it's
just very like normal buildings the
final thing I learned is that people are
going to give you all kinds of advice
and I think that it's really easy to
take that advice because you walk into a
room and there's like Google's first
stock certificate and you know they're
like invented Yahoo like these people
are really really really smart but if
you look at the returns on venture
capital it's pretty shaky like we're in
a pretty high volatility industry and
one thing that we always told ourselves
and one thing that I really really
believe is that fundamentally like the
future is unwritten like if they knew
they would be done right and so people
can tell you that you should be more
technical they can tell you that you're
in the wrong market they can tell you
all of these things and those things
might be true and you should assess them
for yourself but you shouldn't take it
on face because they could be wrong and
in the back of your head you have to
remember something that for all the
millions of dollars venture capital
investors have made for all the
certificates that are on the wall they
are these little trophies when things go
IPO for all those things there are
things that they passed on and those are
the things that actually burn them up
like those are the ones that like haunt
them at night and I think that if you
can convince somebody that you just
might be the one that's going to beat
the odds you can be successful and it's
a general attitude that I think is
important whether you're recruiting
whether you're raising money whether you
just need to make a final push in
adjusting your product so eventually we
put money together and we were working
back on toe we were still having the
same fundamental problem that we
couldn't iterate and improve fast enough
and we were fundraising on the East
Coast and while I was out there I met
this really great guy named Evan sharp
Evan is a Columbia graduate student at
the time he's studying architecture and
we just hit it off and Evan and Paul and
I are commiserating about this whole
dilemma and we're just thinking about
what would be cool to build like what do
we just want to see and really what we
wanted to see was we wanted to see
something out there in the world we just
wanted to see somebody using something
somebody asked me once like what's my
what's my big plan like what would make
me really happy when we were starting
Pinterest I was like geez I just want to
go somewhere and see somebody that I
don't know using something that I made
and have it be kind of useful like that
is what I thought was really exciting
and so we came up with this idea for
something that was web-based really
simple something that we would use
personally and that was Pinterest we
learned a lesson from doing the iPhone
app and it was that even though we had
all these ideas of all these great
features that were cramming in we
weren't great at one thing right there
wasn't one thing that was special about
it people talk a lot about like a
Minimum Viable Product or when you
should ship something and my advice is
you should ship when you have one thing
that you're proud of like one thing that
is worthy of someone's time and that
could take you a long time and it could
take you not very long at all but if
it's not worth their time to check out
you're not going to get any good
feedback on whether it's good or not
they're going to see it they're going to
be like this is crap thank you for the
feedback start again and we decided that
the one thing we had to do really well
if we were going to make a website about
collections we had to make it look
really cool like if it didn't look cool
but no one's going to make a collection
because they don't want to show their
friends because this thing they just
made looks really lame so this is the
first version of Pinterest it didn't
look very cool and November 2009 we
started building the basic
infrastructure and started really
iterating on what it could look like how
could we make it look really interesting
so we went through a lot of versions of
this vertical grid horizontal grid both
left side nav right side nav top nav
different logos and we waited until we
felt we had something that we thought
was really cool and we would show it to
people along the way we would show them
something that we thought was a little
bit of an improvement and we finally
felt ready to launch it I emailed out to
all my friends like all my family I'm
like look at this really cool thing
we're really jazzed about it and
basically no one responded right there's
basically no response at all 3,000
accounts not active users account is
pretty bad if you have three people
actively pushing it out to every single
person they know every day for four
months but there was something that was
really positive and it was that the few
people that used it myself amongst them
actually really loved it
and instead of immediately changing the
product I was like maybe I can just find
more people like me and that also fits
with our current operating strategy
since we don't have very good
engineering resources so we're just
going to market this thing and that's
what we started to do we started to have
meetups to serve first meetup in San
Francisco it was at a store called rare
device we did another meet up later at
West Elm it's a little bit later we all
try to make it fun do fun pictures and
we also market it online so we had a
campaign with a blogger that I had met
named Victoria who's a wonderful woman
and we had something called pin it
forward where everyone would create a
pinboard about what home meant to them
it was organized like a chain letter
like one person would introduce the next
person would introduce the next person
and everyone who participated would get
invites to invite other people and the
thing about it that really worked was we
found this little group of people that
were interested in the same thing and we
showed them how the service could be
helpful to them and fundamentally that's
what Pinterest is about it's about
finding people who share common
interests and those people may be your
friends they may not be your friends but
we needed a different strategy for going
at it than all the strategies that we
were reading about in terms of general
social sites so it's a really really
exciting moment for us and the best
moment of all was when things started to
grow when we went to that Meetup even
though we had very very few users I
distinctly remember the people hadn't
met each other before we're having real
conversations right they weren't
conversations they were asking
about things in their life that they
never would have known if they were just
following each other on Twitter or if
they were just looking at each other's
Facebook projects they found people they
were saying hey how's the gardening
project that you're working on how's
your new living room how's all that
stuff going and it felt like that was
the kernel of something really special
the idea that you could use a service
online that you found out about you
could go to a physical place and you
could find that same person and you had
a genuine connection a lot of people in
Silicon Valley didn't get and I still
don't know if they really get Pinterest
a lot of them kind of looked at it they
said well it's visual it's not organized
in real-time which was a big theme back
then it doesn't have a feed like it
didn't really make sense to them why
anyone would use it but the fact that it
made sense to someone was what really
mattered to me and I think it ties back
to what I told you guys about
investors a lot of people are reading
tech press investors read the same
hacker news articles that everyone reads
there's not some secret special hacker
news that has the real companies that
you want to invest in they're reading
the same TechCrunch articles they're
getting the same data it's incredibly
democratic you have access to all the
information they have access to and that
also means that just like anyone else
they may be subject to the same biases
and trends and bubbles and reports that
happen in the general consumer media at
the time we were like the polar opposite
of what people wanted to see Twitter
FriendFeed Facebook were the hot
companies right because they were
real-time
Google was like we need to do real-time
search everything had to be a text-based
feed that could be accessed on your
phone and here we come and we're saying
it's not real-time it's all visual and
so if they're drawing they're 2 by 2
matrix they're like this is a disaster
right this is like the worst thing that
could happen and eventually what we can
tell them eventually is we would show
them real users and eventually those
users were their wives or eventually
their users were people they knew when
there were life and that's when it
became a lot easier to get things done
so where are we today we live in San
Francisco now we just moved her office
from Palo Alto sadly I love Palo Alto
and we're building out a team of people
that are really diverse I mean I think
the thing that we learned in building
the service was that our problem and
distribution was an engineering problem
it was a community problem the problem
in building the first really cool thing
didn't happen to be anything but a
design problem and those three things
just had to work together for our kind
of business to succeed when I came out
of Google I thought man the only way I
can get this done if I get the most
brilliant graduate student out of
Stanford who doesn't know that he's
invented PageRank yet get him into a
room and we'll just build all this
really really awesome stuff we call our
company called brew labs because all the
cool companies call themselves labs
right we're like like oh my god we got
to be labs or no one is going to want to
work here it's like labs companies are
really cool and one of the most kind of
satisfying realizations is that there
are a lot of different ways to succeed
there are a lot of different companies
there are companies that don't raise
money they're companies that do raise
money they're companies that go b2b
their company
that our consumer and then within
consumer there are a lot of different
things that are successful for the very
simple reason that there are a lot of
different kinds of people in the world
and as much as people want to give you
advice about exactly how you should run
your startup exactly the strategy I
think you need to trust the data you
need to trust the users that you have
and you need to trust your own instinct
to do what you think is going to be
right for your company
Pinterest right now is a tool where we
help people find their inspiration into
some people that sounds really hokey but
to me the idea that we can show people
things that they want to do in their
future help them get closer to actually
doing those things whether it's
redecorating their home or going on a
vacation or buying a gift and in that
process inspire someone else is a really
cool thing to be working on and it's not
what we thought the site was going to do
when we first launched it but it's what
it's come to be and sometimes the
product finds its purpose and sometimes
it goes the other way around
and either way is okay as long as you
get to something that people really love
Pinterest is a network right we have
millions of people that are connected
through billions of objects it's the
third largest source of referral traffic
on the internet and so in the early days
when people like we don't need to be a
technology company now we have to write
all of a sudden now we need folks that
can mine for data and those people have
really interesting things to do like
we're on that road trip like we're
heading towards the Midwest and turns
out we had to view the other way and I
think that adaptability to change is
really fundamental and at the same time
Pinterest is a tool where people can do
these things right you can plan a
vacation you can plan cooking and
recipes you can plan holiday shopping
you can plan all these things in your
life and the very last thing that's
important to me is that Pinterest is a
team of talented people like I feel
genuinely lucky like walk into the
office and work with people that are
better than me at pretty much everything
I do and I think that to me even though
there are a lot of stories told about
entrepreneurs the toil alone the best
things in the world are made by groups
of people I think when you're really
early on startup you're really worried
about oh my gosh like I can't give my
equity to this person it's going to run
out but it's that size of the total pie
right it's it's the size of how many
people can you actually build something
that's bigger than who they are and if
you can find those
people if you can find people that want
to work with you on something that's
bigger than they are I think that it's
the best investment that you can make to
give them ownership in what you're
actually building and to me it's just
been a really gratifying experience to
know that everyone that works with us
actually owns part of the fate of the
company so this is just people from
around the office we obviously value
collaboration it's kind of how the
company was founded and so if I had two
pieces of advice there they're really
really simple right the first is that
you should really just build something
you believe in if you're going to go on
a five-year seven-year 10-year 15 year
journey at least build something that
you really really love because otherwise
you're definitely going to burn out
right you'd have to be like the most
mercenary person to give themselves 15
years and take all this risk if you
didn't at least love the idea of where
you're going to end up and the second is
just don't give up don't let somebody
talk you out of your dream and the
reason that I think startup school is so
cool is because if you look around in
the room like you're surrounded by all
these people that really want to do what
you're doing
Silicon Valley is like a weird place
like people always seem to be talking
about doing startups but people are from
all over the country they're from all
over the world and those early parts of
doing a start-up can actually be really
lonely can just be a total bummer
because you're toiling on this thing no
one cares about it it's not getting
anywhere and there's a tendency I think
with a lot of people that I meet are
doing startups that are like I just need
to work harder I need to go out into the
world less I need to turn on a life less
frequently maybe I need to sit closer to
the screen and I think that it's a
really dangerous game to play like
there's a reason that I started the
presentation by showing a really good
friend of mine who wasn't working at the
company I was but was still hanging out
with us all the time the fact that we
could get a beer and talk about hey this
is really tough this is a hard time made
it a lot easier and wherever you live
the great thing now is that you can find
those people like they may be in your
neighborhoods they may be online they
may be some part of a meet-up
but you can find those people somewhere
and I personally think it's good advice
to take the time and to invest in those
people so part of the reason I was so
excited to come was to me it's just
really exciting to be in a room full of
so many people to basically want to do
what I want to do right
I basically just want to build something
bigger than myself that a lot of people
in the world will find useful and to be
with lots of those people just makes me
happy it gets me excited about doing
what we do every day